On your path toward Enlightenment, you should
first and foremost understand the principle.
I see you're practicing without
understanding the principles behind it.
To practice without knowing the principles
is like hiking up a mountain without
knowing your way around it.
You should first understand the principles.
That said, understanding
the principles is not enough.
Wrongdoings based on ignorance can
be fixed as long as you become aware.
And yet habits of the mind and body,
karma cannot be fixed that easily.
Why not? It is because
we subconsciously go back to our old ways.
There's an anecdote of general
Kim Yushin of the Silla dynasty.
As a young man, he frequented
the geisha houses when he got drunk.
When his father found out,
he was seriously reprimanded.
So he swore to his father
that he'd never go back.
But one day, he got drunk and fell asleep
on horseback. And what happened?
The horse naturally headed to the geisha
house on its own. Do you know the story?
(Audience) Yes.
This is what I'm talking about.
You think to yourself,
'I shouldn't get mad',
but your anger comes out first.
You're nagging others
before you even know it.
You understand the principles
but lose hold of the moment,
just like how the horse followed
its old routine.
So what did the general do in the story?
He pulled out his sword and slew the horse.
Telling yourself that you'll start
anew tomorrow doesn't work
You need to slay the horse then and there.
In other words, you need to cut off
your karma right then and there.
Recognize right away
that you got caught up,
and that you are insisting
you are right once again.
If you miss the moment to recognize,
acknowledge it during prayers
and promise yourself
that you won't repeat
the same mistake.
You'll likely lose your vigilance and make
the same mistake over and over again.
Don't give up when this happens.
True practice refers to
only those who strive for it
even after failing 100 times,
1000 times.
You fall back on your old ways
even if you don't intend to.
It subconsciously happens,
there's no use crying over it.
So be mindful and aware,
and continue disciplining yourself.
This is what we call practice.
When children learn how to ride a bike,
do they start riding right away?
They don't, they inevitably fall.
But if they cry and give up
after having fallen a few times,
they'll never learn to ride.
Riding requires constant practice.
Only after many stumbles
can they start riding.
You fail again and again, and then
some more. Only then can you succeed.
In that sense, is failing
not a step towards success?
(Audience) It is.
(Sunim) It's a step towards success
from a positive standpoint.
Knowing that failure means you're one step
closer to success is being positive.
Giving up only leads to
frustration and despair.
Don't give up without trying, saying
"Well, form is emptiness
and emptiness is form anyway."
You shouldn't apply dharma like that.
To practice until you succeed,
to persevere knowing that failure
is a step towards success
This is how we should live as optimists.
If you fall, laugh if off and pick
yourself up. Don't stay down crying.
In the same manner, regard the anguishes
in your mind as natural occurrences.
Don't take issues with them.
They occur for a reason.
So don't try to resist or eliminate them.
If you truly repent,
they'll naturally disappear.
If you don't repent sincerely,
then these anguishes
will take over your mind.
Hence when you notice you're distracted
during your prayers,
take it as a sign and truly repent.
Only then can true form of
repentance come to you.
Right now, you're forcing
repentance upon yourself.
You're saying, "I've done you
wrong, my husband. It's my fault."
But deep in your subconscious,
you're thinking 'Why the hell
should I be sorry when he is to blame?'
You're running into resistance.
If you forge on from this resistance and
continue to self-reflect and lower
yourself, one day you'll come to realize.
'Ah, how stubborn was I!
How hurt he must have felt.'
Only then will you truly understand.
The tears you then shed will neither
be of sorrow nor resentment.
Tears of true repentance
brighten up the face.
They are tears of true realization.
They come from a brightened place
rather than sorrow,
hence they stop flowing shortly after.
The former tears you've shed
were tears of sorrow and resentment,
hence they wouldn't stop.
The root cause of those
emotions were still there.
Once you truly repent,
you become light-hearted,
and tears come to an end.
You might cry over other things,
but you no longer will for this matter.
So going back, we should first listen
to dharma and understand the principles.
This we call 'beholding the truth'.
Secondly, we should act
according to principles.
To strive and practice persistently
based on principles, this we call
'cultivation of the way'.
As we behold the truth and cultivate,
we should apply and experience
learnings in real life.
You and I are all somewhere
in the middle of this process.
Hence we shouldn't criticize others saying
"You've been a Buddhist all these years,
yet you only talk the talk".
There's always a distance
between knowing and doing.
We're all striving to bridge
the gap between the two.
We shouldn't judge others
on how they aren't practicing
what they know of.
Recognize their diligence in trying,
don't comment on
whether they are failing or not.
We all fail,
there's no reason to
criticize others for it.
In the same sense, don't try to teach
others on how to practice.
If someone seeks advice, just say
"Yeah, it's difficult for me too."
When people ask me for advice,
I say "It's hard for me too."
I never say, "Why can't
you do this and that?"
I say, "I know, I have troubles myself
with distractions during meditation."
I fail too, but it's not a bad thing.
It's just part of life,
and all we can do is persevere.
Hence we need not judge
others on their practice,
but should only focus on our own.
When asked for advice, we should only share
our own experiences without judging others.
This is why one of the precepts
of Jungto is, "Do not teach others."
This doesn't refer
to teaching of a skill set.
It means that we shouldn't criticize
nor comment on other's practices.
If someone is struggling
with marital issues,
don't say, "You should
repent to your husband."
Just hear them out,
share your own experiences on things
you've tried based on Sunim's teachings.
Say "Doing such and such
helped me through my issues",
but don't say "You should try it too."
If the person says
"Maybe I should try it too",
only then should you say,
"Yeah, maybe you should."
Don't assess their way of practice,
do you understand?
(Audience) Yes.
We need to perceive
our own shortcomings.
And yet we occasionally see those
that attend Jungto dharma talks
and apply them to others instead.
They say to others, "Sunim said this
and that, why aren't you following it?"
That's not how it should be. Focus only
on yourself and do not judge others.
The previous question raised
relates to this very issue.
While the questioner's
intentions were good,
he's ultimately speaking of others.
In such moments, look within yourself.
We tend to look at other people, when we
should actually be looking within ourselves.
"Sunim, see how he's talking about others
and not looking within himself."
This may sound right,
but is again a form of judgement
towards others.
Don't interfere in other's affairs,
look within yourself.
Only then can we walk the path
to enlightenment and Nirvana.